Well, it's time to get back to it and finish what we started.
Our arcade game is fun, but it's missing that crucial element that takes you from being a kind of fun
game to a really fun game.
And this is what polishing is all about.
It's the final stage of our workflow.
So for the first step of polishing, we are going to make our graphics a bit better, make our game
feel much more real.
The first thing we want to discuss is layers.
We briefly discussed this in an earlier lesson, but let's run over it again.
So in scratch, each of our sprites appear on our screen with an x and Y position, as you know.
Now this is easy to see, but our sprites also have a z axis, which we can't easily see as everything
is 2D and we are looking from a top down view.
We basically the z axis is the layer.
So imagine a stack of papers.
You might have 20 pieces of paper on top of one another and each has its layer.
So if the paper is on the top of the pile, it is at layer one, and if it's on the bottom, it's layer
20.
And naturally, if a paper is at a higher layer like layer one, it will cover the paper that is at
a lower layer like layer two.
So the exact same thing happens in scratch when our sprites are on different layers.
So if we play our game quickly and if we crash into a tree, you will see that, well, we kind of ski
over the tree, which doesn't make sense.
So how do we fix this?
Well, if we move over to our player sprite, we can grab another when flag clicked and then move up
to the looks tab.
Here we will see we have two options.
Either we can make it go to the front or back, or we can have it go backwards or forwards a layer.
So if we were to say go to back and then hit play.
As you can see, our snow trail goes in front of us, so this isn't an option.
So let's bring this back to the front.
Like this.
Now, this time we can instead say go back one layer.
So now, rather than sending this to the very back, we'll just moving it back one layer, which means
our player sprite will be in layer two.
Now dragging the script over to both our snow pixels, we can have it go backwards two layers, and
we can also do the same for the other sprite.
Clicking play.
Well that's weird.
Our picks are listed in front.
Hmm.
Any ideas what's happening here?
Well, the reason for this is because each time we start the game, it keeps going back more and more
layers.
So what we need to do is go to each of these sprites and bring in this go to front layer, just like
that.
And we can also do the same for our tree sprite.
We can just drag in a when flag clicked and then a go to front layer.
So now this way, when we start our game, each of our sprites starts on the same layer, but our player
moves back one and our pixels go back two.
So trying this out.
As you can see, it works perfectly.
When we crash into a tree, we don't glide in front of it.
Now that's much more realistic.
So with that out of the way, there is one more thing we need to do.
When we play the game.
As you can see, our trees kind of just pop into view, which is a bit jarring.
Wouldn't it be better if they kind of faded in, almost like there was a mist and they were coming into
view from the mist?
Sounds great, but it sounds like a rather complex task.
But fear not, because there is a fairly simple way to do this.
If you look over at our looks group, you will see this change color or set color to.
Dragging the set color effect into our player sprite.
You'll see that if we click it, oh, nothing happens.
But if we change this number to say, 40, our sprite changes color and it almost looks like an alien.
But this isn't what we want so we can set it back to zero.
But you will see that if we click here, there are all these other options.
And the effect we are interested in is this ghost effect.
So let's set it to 95 and clicking it you will see how sprite almost fades out.
So we can use this to fade in our trees.
So quickly resetting it.
We then can move over to our tree sprite.
Now this is your next mini challenge.
Try and see if you can create this effect where our trees fade into view instead of just suddenly appearing.
Come on, give it a try before we show you how to do it.
Did you get it?
Now let's see how it's done.
Now, what we want to happen is when our sprite starts as a clone, we want to set the ghost effect
to 95.
Then to make it fade in, what we are going to do is grab this change effect by block and again set
it to ghost.
Here.
We want to drag it into this forever loop so that the ghosting slowly fades out, which makes it look
like our trees are fading in.
To do this, we need to change this value because currently our ghosting is at 95 and we want to bring
it back to zero.
So we can just enter in minus three here or whatever looks best for you.
So let's give this a test.
You can see that our trees now look like they are slowly appearing into view from the mist.
And yes, it's a very subtle effect, but it just makes our game that much better.
So that's it for now.
If you can see any other areas where you think the graphics can be improved, I encourage you to give
it a go and see what you can do.